boarded a bus in Delhi with her male friend. There were six men on the bus, young men who you might encounter every day in India, and the chilling account of what followed was played over and over again in the Indian and international media. This girl was raped repeatedly, forcefully penetrated with a blunt rod, beaten, bitten, and left to die. Her friend was gagged, attacked,
subió a un autobús en Delhi con su amigo. Había 6 hombres jóvenes en el autobús que una podría encontrar a diario en India, y el escalofriante relato de lo que siguió se mostró una y otra vez en los medios indios e internacionales. Esta joven fue violada reiteradamente, penetrada por la fuerza con una varilla, golpeada, mordida, hasta morir. Su amigo, amordazado, atacado
and knocked unconscious. She died on the 29th of December. And at a time when most of us here were preparing to welcome the new year, India plunged into darkness. For the first time in our history, men and women in Indian cities woke up to the horrific truth about the true state of women in the country. Now, like many other young women, I was absolutely terrified. I couldn't believe that something like this could happen in a national capital. I was angry and I was frustrated, but most of all, I felt utterly, completely helpless. But really, what do you do, right? Some write blogs, some ignore it, some join protests. I did all of it. In fact, that was what everyone was doing two years ago. So the media was filled with stories about all the horrific deeds that Indian men are capable of. They were compared to animals, sexually repressed beasts. In fact, so alien and unthinkable was this event in an Indian mind that the response from the Indian media, public and politicians proved one point: No one knew what to do. And no one wanted to be responsible for it. In fact, these were a few insensitive comments which were made in the media by prominent people in response to sexual violence against women in general. So the first one is made by a member of parliament, the second one is made by a spiritual leader, and the third one was actually the defendants' lawyer when the girl was fighting for her life and she passed away. Now, as a woman watching this day after day, I was tired. So as a writer and gender activist, I have written extensively on women, but this time, I realized it was different, because a part of me realized I was a part of that young woman too, and I decided I wanted to change this. So I did something spontaneous, hasty. I logged on to a citizen journalism platform called iReport, and I recorded a video talking about what the scene was like in Bangalore. I talked about how I felt, I talked about the ground realities, and I talked about the frustrations of living in India. In a few hours, the blog was shared widely, and comments and thoughts poured in from across the world. In that moment, a few things occurred to me. One, technology was always at hand for many young women like me. Two, like me, most young women hardly use it to express their views. Three, I realized for the first time that my voice mattered. So in the months that followed, I covered a trail of events in Bangalore which had no space in the mainstream news. In Cubbon Park, which is a big park in Bangalore, I gathered with over 100 others when groups of young men came forward to wear skirts to prove that clothing does not invite rape. When I reported about these events, I felt I had charge, I felt like I had a channel to release all the emotions I had inside me. I attended the town hall march when students held up signs saying "Kill them, hang them." "You wouldn't do this to your mothers or sisters." I went to a candlelight vigil where citizens gathered together to talk about the issue of sexual violence openly, and I recorded a lot of blogs in response to how worrying the situation was in India at that point. ["I am born with sisters and cousin who now live in cities and abroad but they never talk to me or complain about their daily difficulties like you say"] Now, the reactions confused me. While supportive comments poured in from across the world, as did vicious ones. So some called me a hypocrite. Some called me a victim, a rape apologist. Some even said I had a political motive. But this one comment kind of describes what we are discussing here today. But I was soon to learn that this was not all. As empowered as I felt with the new liberty that this citizen journalism channel gave me, I found myself in an unfamiliar situation. So sometime last August, I logged onto Facebook and I was looking through my news feed, and I noticed there was a link that was being shared by my friends. I clicked on the link; it led me back to a report uploaded by an American girl called Michaela Cross. The report was titled, "India: The story you never wanted to hear." And in this report, she recounted her firsthand account of facing sexual harassment in India. She wrote, "There is no way to prepare for the eyes, the eyes that every day stared with such entitlement at my body, with no change of expression whether I met their gaze or not. Walking to the fruit seller's or the tailor's, I got stares so sharp that they sliced away bits of me piece by piece." She called India a traveler's heaven and a woman's hell. She said she was stalked, groped, and masturbated at. Now, late that evening, the report went viral. It was on news channels across the world. Everyone was discussing it. It had over a million views, a thousand comments and shares, and I found myself witnessing a very similar thing. The media was caught in this vicious cycle of opinion and outburst and no outcome whatsoever. So that night, as I sat wondering how I should respond, I found myself filled with doubt. You see, as a writer, I approached this issue as an observer, as an Indian, I felt embarrassment and disbelief, and as an activist, I looked at it as a defender of rights, but as a citizen journalist, I suddenly felt very vulnerable. I mean, here she was, a young woman who was using a channel to talk about her experience just as I was, and yet I felt unsettled. You see, no one ever tells you that true empowerment comes from giving yourself the permission to think and act. Empowerment is often made to sound as if it's an ideal, it's a wonderful outcome. When we talk about empowerment, we often talk about giving people access to materials, giving them access to tools. But the thing is, empowerment is an emotion. It's a feeling. The first step to empowerment is to give yourself the authority, the key to independent will, and for women everywhere, no matter who we are or where we come from, that is the most difficult step. We fear the sound of our own voice, for it means admission, but it is this that gives us the power to change our environment. Now in this situation where I was faced with so many different kinds of realities, I was unsure how to judge, because I didn't know what it would mean for me. I feared to judge because I didn't know what it would be if I didn't support the same view as this girl. I didn't know what it would mean for me if I was challenging someone else's truth. But yet, it was simple. I had to make a decision: Should I speak up or should I stay quiet? So after a lot of thought, I recorded a video blog in response, and I told Michaela, well, there are different sides to India, and I also tried to explain that things would be okay and I expressed my regret for what she had faced. And a few days later, I was invited to talk on air with her, and for the first time, I reached out to this girl who I had never met, who was so far away, but yet I felt so close to. Since this report came to light, more young people than ever were discussing sexual harassment on the campus, and the university that Michaela belonged to gave her the assistance she needed. The university even took measures to train its students to equip them with the skills that they need to confront challenges such as harassment, and for the first the time, I felt I wasn't alone. You see, if there's anything that I've learned as an active citizen journalist over the past few years, it is our dire lack as a society to actively find avenues where our voices can be heard. We don't realize that when we are standing up, we are not just standing up as individuals, we are standing up for our communities, our friends, our peers. Most of us say that women are denied their rights, but the truth is, oftentimes, women deny themselves these rights. In a recent survey in India, 95 percent of the women who work in I.T., aviation, hospitality and call centers, said they didn't feel safe returning home alone after work in the late hours or in the evening. In Bangalore, where I come from, this number is 85 percent. In rural areas in India, if anything is to go by the recent gang rapes in Badaun and acid attacks in Odisha and Aligarh are supposed to go by, we need to act really soon. Don't get me wrong, the challenges that women will face in telling their stories is real, but we need to start pursuing and trying to identify mediums to participate in our system and not just pursue the media blindly. Today, more women than ever are standing up and questioning the government in India, and this is a result of that courage. There is a sixfold increase in women reporting harassment, and the government passed the Criminal Law (Amendment) Act in 2013 to protect women against sexual assault. As I end this talk, I just want to say that I know a lot of us in this room have our secrets, but let us speak up. Let us fight the shame and talk about it. It could be a platform, a community, your loved one, whoever or whatever you choose, but let us speak up. The truth is, the end to this problem begins with us. Thank you. (Applause)
y golpeado, quedó inconsciente. Ella murió el 29 de diciembre. Y mientras muchos de los presentes nos disponíamos a recibir el año nuevo, India se sumía en la oscuridad. Por primera vez en nuestra historia, hombres y mujeres de India despertamos a la horrible verdad del estado de las mujeres en el país. Como muchas otras jóvenes, yo estaba aterrada. No podía creer que algo así ocurriese en una capital nacional. Me enojé y estaba frustrada, pero sobre todo, me sentí completamente indefensa. Pero realmente, qué hacer, ¿no? Algunos escriben blogs, otros lo ignoran, algunos protestan. Yo hice todo eso. Era lo que todos hacían hace 2 años. Los medios estaban repletos de historias de los actos horribles de los que los hombres indios eran capaces. Se los comparó con animales, bestias sexuales reprimidas. Tan ajeno e impensable era este acontecimiento para la mentalidad india que la respuesta de los medios indios, el público y los políticos mostraron que nadie sabía qué hacer. Nadie asumía la responsabilidad. Estos son algunos comentarios insensibles que aparecieron en los medios, de gente importante ["La violación de jovencitas es entendible pero la de los niños, inimaginable"] ["Las chicas deberían llamar hermanos a los violadores"] El primero pertenece a un parlamentario, el segundo a un líder espiritual, y el tercero ["Las víctimas de violación de Delhi son las culpables"] a un abogado de los acusados mientras la joven fallecía. Como mujer, ver esto a diario, me cansó. Como escritora y activista de cuestiones de género, he escrito mucho sobre la mujer, pero esta vez me di cuenta de que era distinto, porque una parte de mí se dio cuenta de que era parte de esa joven también, y decidí que quería cambiar esto. Así que hice algo espontáneo, apresurado. Me conecté a una plataforma de periodismo ciudadano llamada iReport, y grabé un video hablando de la situación en Bangalore. Conté cómo me sentía, conté las realidades sobre el terreno, y hablé de las frustraciones de vivir en India. En pocas horas, el blog se compartió ampliamente y llegaron comentarios y pensamientos de todo el mundo. En ese momento, se me ocurrieron algunas cosas. Una, la tecnología siempre estaba disponible para jóvenes como yo. Dos, que al igual que yo, raramente las jóvenes como yo expresan sus opiniones. Tres, me di cuenta por primera vez de que mi voz importa. Por eso en los meses siguientes, cubrí una serie de eventos en Bangalore que no eran noticia en los medios principales En Cubbon Park, un gran parque de Bangalore, me reuní con otras 100 personas cuando un grupo de jóvenes se pusieron faldas para demostrar que la ropa no invita a la violación. Cuando informé estos eventos, sentí que tenía un canal para liberar las emociones que tenía dentro. Fui a la marcha de la alcaldía en la que los estudiantes tenían pancartas que decían: "Mátenlos, cuélguenlos". "No le harían esto a sus madres o hermanas". Fui a una vigilia con velas donde los ciudadanos se reunieron a hablar abiertamente sobre la violencia sexual, y recuerdo muchos blogs en respuesta a lo preocupante de la situación. ["Mis hermanas y primas viven en ciudades y en el extranjero, pero ni hablaron ni se quejaron de las dificultades que dices"] Esas reacciones me confundieron. Así como llegaban comentarios de apoyo de todo el mundo, también hubo comentarios maliciosos. Algunos me llamaron hipócrita. Decían que yo hacía apología de la víctima, de la violación. Algunos incluso me dijeron que tenía motivación política. Este comentario describe lo que discutimos hoy. Pero no tardé en advertir que esto no era todo. Empoderada como me sentía con la nueva libertad que este canal de periodismo ciudadano me daba, me encontré en una situación desconocida. En agosto pasado, entré a Facebook, estaba mirando las novedades, y advertí que había un enlace compartido por mis amigos. Hice clic en el enlace y me llevó a un informe subido por una chica de EE. UU. llamada Michaela Cross. El informe se titulaba: "India: La historia que nunca quisieras escuchar". En ese informe contaba de primera mano el acoso sexual en India. Escribió: "No hay manera de prepararse para los ojos, los ojos que cada día clavan la mirada con tanto descaro sobre mi cuerpo, sin cambio de expresión, les devuelva o no la mirada. Al caminar a la frutería o la modista recibo miradas tan penetrantes que podrían cortarme en trozos, rodaja por rodaja". Llamaba a India, el paraíso del viajero y el infierno de la mujer. Dijo que fue objeto de miradas, toques, y masturbaciones. Más tarde esa noche, el informe se hizo viral. Estaba en las noticias de todo el mundo. Todo el mundo lo discutía. Tuvo más de un millón de vistas, mil comentarios y referencias, y yo misma presencié algo muy similar. Los medios cayeron en este ciclo vicioso de opinión y arrebatos, sin resultados. Esa noche, viendo cómo debería responder, estaba llena de dudas. Verán, como escritora, encaraba este tema como observadora, como india, sentía vergüenza e incredulidad, y como activista, lo veía como defensora de derechos, pero como periodista ciudadana, me sentí muy vulnerable. Digo, aquí estaba ella, una mujer joven que usaba un canal para hablar de su experiencia como hacía yo, y aún así yo estaba inquieta. Nunca nadie te dice que el verdadero empoderamiento viene de darse uno el permiso para pensar y actuar. A menudo, el empoderamiento suena a ideal, a resultado maravilloso. A menudo, al hablar de empoderamiento, hablamos de darle a las personas acceso a materiales, acceso a herramientas. Pero, el empoderamiento es una emoción. Es un sentimiento. El primer paso para el empoderamiento es darse uno mismo la autoridad, la clave de la voluntad independiente, y para las mujeres de todas partes, sin importar quiénes seamos o de dónde venimos, ese es el paso más difícil. Le tememos al sonido de nuestra propia voz, porque significa admisión, pero es ella la que nos da el poder de cambiar el entorno. En esta situación en la cual enfrentaba tantas realidades diferentes, no sabía cómo juzgar porque yo no sabía qué significaría para mí. Temía juzgar porque no sabía qué pasaría si no apoyaba la misma mirada de esta chica. No sabía qué significaría para mí desafiar la verdad del otro. Pero, sin embargo, era simple. Tuve que tomar una decisión: ¿Debería hablar o permanecer en silencio? Después de mucho pensarlo, grabé un video en respuesta, y le dije a Michaela, bueno, que India tiene varios aspectos, y también traté de explicarle que las cosas estarían bien y le expresé mi pesar por lo que había enfrentado. Unos días después, me invitaron a hablar al aire con ella, y por primera vez, me acerqué a esta chica que no conocía, que estaba tan lejos, pero que sentía tan cercana. Desde que salió a la luz este informe, más cantidad de jóvenes que nunca discutían sobre acoso sexual en el campus, y la universidad a la que pertenecía Michaela le dio la asistencia que necesitaba. La universidad tomó incluso las medidas para entrenar a sus estudiantes en las habilidades que necesitaban para enfrentar desafíos como el acoso, y, por primera vez, sentí que no estaba sola. Si algo aprendí como periodista ciudadana activa en los años pasados, es nuestra grave falta como sociedad para buscar activamente vías de expresión para nuestras voces. No nos damos cuenta de que al reclamar, no lo hacemos como individuos, sino como comunidad, en nombre de nuestros amigos y pares. Muchos decimos que se le niegan los derechos a la mujer, pero a menudo la verdad es que las propias mujeres nos negamos estos derechos. En una encuesta reciente en India, el 95 % de las mujeres que trabajan en TI, aviación, hotelería y centros de llamadas, dijeron no sentirse a salvo de regreso a casa solas luego de trabajar hasta altas horas o por la tarde. En Bangalore, de donde vengo, este número es el 85 %. En zonas rurales de India, a juzgar por las recientes violaciones en grupo en Badaun y ataques con ácido en Odisha y Aligarh, tenemos que actuar realmente pronto. No me malinterpreten, los desafíos que enfrentarán las mujeres al contar sus historias son reales, pero tenemos que empezar a buscar y tratar de identificar los medios para participar en nuestro sistema y no solo buscar los medios a ciegas. Hoy, más mujeres que nunca reclaman y cuestionan al gobierno indio, y esto es resultado de ese coraje. Hay un aumento de 6 veces en la denuncia de acoso de mujeres, y el gobierno indio aprobó la enmienda al Código Penal en 2013 para proteger a las mujeres contra el ataque sexual. Para terminar esta charla solo quiero decir que sé que todos tenemos secretos, pero hablemos en voz alta. Venzamos la vergüenza y hablemos de ello. Podría ser en una plataforma, en una comunidad, con los seres queridos, donde y con quienes queramos, pero hablemos en voz alta. La verdad es que al final este problema empieza por nosotros. Gracias. (Aplausos)